And it's then, when you're lost or uneasy or carried out of yourself, that you find out who you are. I don't believe that ignorance is bliss. Science has unquestionably made our lives brighter and longer and healthier. And I am forever grateful to the teachers who showed me the laws of physics and pointed out that three times three makes nine. I can count that out on my fingers any time of night or day. But when a mathematician tells me that minus three times minus three makes nine, that's a kind of logic that almost feels like trust. The opposite of knowledge, in other words, isn't always ignorance. It can be wonder. Or mystery. Possibility. And in my life, I've found it's the things I don't know that have lifted me up and pushed me forwards much more than the things I do know. It's also the things I don't know that have often brought me closer to everybody around me. For eight straight Novembers, recently, I traveled every year across Japan with the Dalai Lama. And the one thing he said every day that most seemed to give people reassurance and confidence was, "I don't know." "What's going to happen to Tibet?" "When are we ever going to get world peace?" "What's the best way to raise children?" "Frankly," says this very wise man, "I don't know." The Nobel Prize-winning economist Daniel Kahneman has spent more than 60 years now researching human behavior, and his conclusion is that we are always much more confident of what we think we know than we should be. We have, as he memorably puts it, an "unlimited ability to ignore our ignorance." We know -- quote, unquote -- our team is going to win this weekend, and we only remember that knowledge on the rare occasions when we're right. Most of the time, we're in the dark. And that's where real intimacy lies. Do you know what your lover is going to do tomorrow? Do you want to know? The parents of us all, as some people call them, Adam and Eve, could never die, so long as they were eating from the tree of life. But the minute they began nibbling from the tree of the knowledge of good and evil, they fell from their innocence. They grew embarrassed and fretful, self-conscious. And they learned, a little too late, perhaps, that there are certainly some things that we need to know, but there are many, many more that are better left unexplored. Now, when I was a kid, I knew it all, of course. I had been spending 20 years in classrooms collecting facts, and I was actually in the information business, writing articles for Time Magazine. And I took my first real trip to Japan for two-and-a-half weeks, and I came back with a 40-page essay explaining every last detail about Japan's temples, its fashions, its baseball games, its soul. But underneath all that, something that I couldn't understand so moved me for reasons I couldn't explain to you yet, that I decided to go and live in Japan. And now that I've been there for 28 years, I really couldn't tell you very much at all about my adopted home. Which is wonderful, because it means every day I'm making some new discovery, and in the process, looking around the corner and seeing the hundred thousand things I'll never know. Knowledge is a priceless gift. But the illusion of knowledge can be more dangerous than ignorance. Thinking that you know your lover or your enemy can be more treacherous than acknowledging you'll never know them. Every morning in Japan, as the sun is flooding into our little apartment, I take great pains not to consult the weather forecast, because if I do, my mind will be overclouded, distracted, even when the day is bright. I've been a full-time writer now for 34 years. And the one thing that I have learned is that transformation comes when I'm not in charge, when I don't know what's coming next, when I can't assume I am bigger than everything around me. And the same is true in love or in moments of crisis. Suddenly, we're back in that trishaw again and we're bumping off the broad, well-lit streets; and we're reminded, really, of the first law of travel and, therefore, of life: you're only as strong as your readiness to surrender. In the end, perhaps, being human is much more important than being fully in the know. Thank you. (Applause)
Y es entonces, cuando se está perdido o incómodo o insatisfecho, que uno descubre quién es. No creo que la ignorancia sea felicidad. La ciencia ha mejorado, sin dudas, nuestras vidas con más salud, más longevidad y vitalidad. Siempre agradezco a los maestros que me mostraron las leyes de la física y que me enseñaron que tres por tres es nueve. Puedo contar eso con mis dedos a cualquier hora del día o de la noche. Pero cuando un matemático me dice que menos tres por menos tres es nueve, esa es una lógica que se parece a la confianza. Es decir, lo contrario al conocimiento no siempre es la ignorancia. Puede ser la maravilla. O el misterio. La posibilidad. Y en mi vida, he encontrado que son las cosas que no conozco las que me han levantado y empujado hacia delante, mucho más que las cosas que sí conozco. Son también las cosas que no conozco las que a menudo me han acercado al mundo que me rodea. Durante ocho noviembres seguidos, recientemente, he viajado cada año por Japón con el Dalai Lama. Y lo único que dijo cada día que pareciera dar tranquilidad y confianza a la gente fue "No sé". "¿Qué va a pasar con el Tíbet?" "¿Cuándo alcanzaremos la paz en el mundo?" "¿Cuál es la mejor manera de educar a los hijos?" "Francamente", dice este hombre muy sabio, "no lo sé". El economista ganador del premio Nobel Daniel Kahneman ha dedicado más de 60 años a investigar la conducta humana, y su conclusión es que siempre estamos mucho más seguros de lo que pensamos que sabemos de lo que deberíamos. Tenemos, como dice de forma memorable, una "capacidad ilimitada de ignorar nuestra ignorancia". Sabemos —cita, fin de cita— que nuestro equipo ganará este fin de semana, y solo recordamos ese conocimiento en las raras ocasiones en las que estamos en lo correcto. La mayoría de las veces, estamos en la oscuridad. Y ahí es donde radica la verdadera intimidad. ¿Saben lo que su amante hará mañana? ¿Quieren saberlo? Los padres de todos nosotros, como algunos les llaman, Adán y Eva, podrían no haber muerto, siempre y cuando comieran del árbol de la vida. Pero desde el momento en que empezaron a comer del árbol del conocimiento del bien y del mal, abandonaron su inocencia. Crecieron avergonzados y quejosos, conscientes de sí mismos. Y aprendieron, demasiado tarde tal vez, que sin dudas hay algunas cosas que debemos saber, pero hay muchas, muchas más que es mejor dejar sin explorar. Ahora, cuando yo era niño, lo sabía todo, por supuesto. Había pasado 20 años en las aulas colectando hechos, en realidad estaba en el mundo de la información, escribiendo artículos para la revista Time. E hice mi primer viaje real a Japón de dos semanas y media, y volví con un ensayo de 40 páginas explicando cada detalle de los templos de Japón, sus modas, sus juegos de béisbol, su alma. Pero debajo de todo eso, algo que no pude entender me conmovió tanto por razones que no podría explicarles, sin embargo, que decidí ir a vivir a Japón. Y ahora que he estado allí durante 28 años, realmente no podría contarles mucho en absoluto sobre mi hogar adoptivo. Que es una maravilla, porque todos los días descubro algo nuevo, y, en el proceso, miro alrededor de la esquina y veo cien mil cosas que nunca conoceré. El conocimiento es un regalo invaluable. Pero la ilusión del conocimiento puede ser más peligrosa que la ignorancia. Pensar que conocen a su amante, o a su enemigo, puede ser más traicionero que reconocer que nunca los conocerán. Cada mañana en Japón, conforme el sol inunda nuestro pequeño apartamento, me empeño mucho en no consultar la previsión del tiempo porque, si lo hago, se nublará mi mente, se distraerá, aunque el día sea brillante. He sido escritor a tiempo completo durante 34 años, y lo único que he aprendido es que la transformación viene cuando no estoy a cargo, cuando no sé lo que vendrá después, cuando no puedo suponer que soy más grande que todo lo que me rodea. Y lo mismo es cierto en el amor, o en momentos de crisis. De repente, estamos de vuelta en ese nuevo trishaw trajinando las amplias y bien iluminadas calles; y se nos recuerda, en realidad, la primera ley del viaje y, por lo tanto, de la vida: uno es tan fuerte como su disposición a rendirse. Al final, tal vez, ser humano es mucho más importante que conocer cabalmente. Gracias. (Aplausos)